<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Devill incarnate, or, A satyr upon a satyr being a display of the hairy devill, countess of bedlam.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12580020</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12580020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 960:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Devill incarnate, or, A satyr upon a satyr being a display of the hairy devill, countess of bedlam.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devil --  Anecdotes</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:63727:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE DEVIIL INCARNATE, OR A <hi>SATYR</hi> upon a <hi>SATYR;</hi> Being a Diſplay of the Hairy Devill, Counteſs of <hi>BEDLAM.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SHe's a thing at firſt ſprung up out of the bottomleſs Pit, was poked out of Hell with a Taylors <hi>Yard,</hi> and is indeed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill every way, as Ugly and as Envious. She's an Old Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole thats kindled at the lower end, and will be burnt out ere long with a Pox to Her. She's an Ugly Pus, a bundle of ſoul Stuff, a filthy Maſs of Guts and Garbage, that lives upon the ſucking of Her Ale-Taps, and the nick and froth of Her penny black Pots. She's a Gallimautry fars'd up with as many ill ingredients as if <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lzebub</hi> and all his legions had ſpent their whole time and ſtudy to compoſe Her. She's the Devills Fire-brand wherewith he keeps a continuall fire in the Hell of Her houſe: and when He caſts her abroad into the open Aire, She flyes about lightning, ſo that the whole Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is like to be in a Combuſtion. And if this were not the fire of Hell even unquenchable fire, ſo many Tuns of Ale as in one day are powred down that unſatiable Gulf of Her Throat, would certainly be enough to quench it. But I remember that very ſtrong Ale will burn when it toucheth the fire, which it muſt needs do when it comes into that Furnace of her Body which is ſeven times hotter then that which was heated for the three Children. And in this She thinks her ſelf very Politick, that of plain Ale She can ſo eaſily make burnt Ale; but She may thank the Devill for that faculty.</p>
            <p>He that hath come once by her door, hath been in the Suburbs of Hell; but he that comes into her houſe, will find an Hell upon earth: I hope
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63727:2"/>no man that's wiſe will come there, unleſs he deſire to have a cure wrought upon his body by ſweating; for 'tis no other then a Stewes or Hot-Houſe, the fire being continually burning: in which reguard it might ſerve for a Chymiſts Shop, or a Glaſs-Houſe; but She rather deals in <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſs</hi> and <hi>Copper,</hi> as I'le tell Her to Her <hi>Face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Airy, the ſure that ſide of your houſe next Her be made of Free-ſtone (and She loves Free-ſtones) for if it be made of combuſtible matter, I am ſure it ſtands in much danger. She's no convenient neighbour to border ſo near upon the Front of a Colledg, for it muſt needs be offenſive and prejudiciall to all Students, to have the Sun perpetually ſhining in their faces She's beneficial only to her ſelf, for her Face will ſupply the want of fewel in the Winter: if ſhe does but look upon the Pot, its enough to make it boyl: and ſhe needs not uſe any candle either day or night, the light of her Countenance is ſo glorious. Wherefore ſhe is an utter enemy to all Chandlers, there's no candle can burn in her preſence, for the greater light alwayes puts out the leſſer: She burns daylight, lights a Torch to the Sun, and ſerves for a Lanthorn at Queens Colledg Gates in the winter nights. She is the Comer or Blazing-Star, which appears over againſt Queens Colledg; and ſometimes would ſeem to portend ſtrang things, but they alwayes prove falſe: or, ſhe's the morning ſtar, <hi>viz. Verus,</hi> and loves to be in conjunction with <hi>Jup-it-her;</hi> and that's the reaſon ſome of her progeny are ſo Venereal.</p>
            <p>Her Face would make a fit Meddall in Copper, upon which for a Motto there ſhould be in Capitalls ingraved IMPUDENCE. Her eyes are two gogling ſparkling Globes, between which and her mouth there's a pretty ſpeckled painted jewel, from whence there daily flows a Cream-pot of Nectar. By her Omega's noſe, ſhe ſhould have been Related to the late Tyrant <hi>Oliver;</hi> and its no great wonder to ſee ſuch a copper Noſe upon a brazen Face: or, by ſome other parts of her, ſhe ſhould have been related to the Hairy woman, I warrant one might get many a pound by ſhewing her naked at Market Towns and Fairs; for no man can eaſily imagine there's ſuch a Monſter in Nature, unleſs he ſee it.</p>
            <p>She can ſing, <hi>Drunk and Sober again,</hi> three or four times a day: the Pot and the Pipe are her ſole delight, and ſeeing they are ſuch loving companions, ſhe ſeldom parts them, &amp; is ſeldom without them: For her mouth is a bottomleſs Pit, from whence the ſmoak continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſcends both day and night: and out of it withall, worſe then the Locuſts, Words ſharper than Arrows, a Tongue more ſharpe then a two edged Sword: And its alwayes wandring about the Town; its worſe then a vipers, is like a ſharp Rafor that cutteth deceitfully, is ſet on Fire of Hell, and full of deadly Poiſon. It is nothing but a burning Link, whoſe flames will kindle upon all things that come near it.</p>
            <p>Her Teeth ſhe borrowed of ſome Horſe or Elephant which had got the Rot, and therefore they will be gon out of Town ere long; her
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63727:2"/>Noſe and her Chin intend to meet about it:</p>
            <p>Her Chin is double like her Tongue; it is ſuch a maſs that if it were tryed, it would afford greaſe enough to make two or three pound of kitchin-ſtuff.</p>
            <p>But to conclude concerning her Face, it muſt be a pretious thing, for 'tis ſet ſo thick with Rubies and Carbuncles, that it would dazle the eyes of an Eagle to behold it.</p>
            <p>Her Head ſtands upon a ſtately Pillar as white as the Reddeſt-Corall: And a little lower are two great boſſes made of leather bottles as big as <hi>Gogmagog Hids,</hi> from which there hang two ſuch Labells or Teats as if the Devill had been ſucking the Witch.</p>
            <p>Her Bum is bigger than any barrel, which ſhe drags after her with a great deal of gravity. As for her belly I cannot deſcrib that, becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come at it, for its convered with hair; which every year ſhe ſhaves off, enough to make forty Merkins: &amp; it is longer than ordinary, or elſe they are lyars that have ſeen it. But leaſt I ſhould come too near her Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I'le go up again to her Hands; for ſhe loves that Hands and Belly ſhould come together. She hath pretty little hands, which will ſerve her for ſmall uſe; but its not much matter, for as it ſeems ſhe was made rather to be handled then to handle. To come a little nearer, Her Belly is a Butt, for all that come to ſhoot at, (<hi>Cupid</hi> hath often ſhot her between <hi>wind</hi> and <hi>water</hi>) and they may have a foul (I had almoſt ſaid a fair) mark, which they may eaſily hit if they pleaſe: yet I will not ſay they may eaſily hit the the white, for ther's no ſuch thing there.</p>
            <p>Her Thighs are not much bigger than the Pillars in St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church; and her Leggs are proportionable, which makes her ſtand to her tacklings ſo well, even as ſhe would have others <hi>Stand</hi> to her. And now I am come to her Foot, I'le trace out her good qualities, which are every whit agreable to the comely proportions of Her Perſon.</p>
            <p>If you know the nature of the Devill, you know hers exactly; for all her ſtudy is calumny and ſlander, in which ſhe takes more delight then in eating her daily bread. She would indeed do all other kinds of miſcheif if it were in her power; but <hi>the curſt Cow hath ſhort horns.</hi> And ſeeing ſhe hath no other Inſtrument then her tongue that ſtands her in much ſtead, ſhe puts that to the moſt uſe that may be, and lets it <hi>alwayes</hi> be wagging.</p>
            <p>Her Throat is an open Sepulcher, wherein lye buried many honeſt peoples Reputations. It is ſo wide that no kind of ly will choak her, though never ſo monſtrons. And in this Art her wit is as pregnant, as if ſhe had lately been at the Devizes: but her Tongue alwayes runs, before her Wit, even as her Invention before her Judgment. She's the moſt abominable of all lyars: ſhe'l lye both backward and forward: the Devill himſelf the Father of lyars cannot out ly her, though any man may eaſily over lye her when he pleaſes. It ſhould ſeem as if ſhe did it for a wager; for ſhe tells the biggeſt and moſt monſtrous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63727:3"/>ſhe can deviſe, and then lyes again in forſwearing them: So that her word and her oath are both alike; for none that knows her will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve her for either any farther then they can ſee her. It was never known yet, that any that ever came near her hath eſcaped the laſh of her ſlandrous Tongue, which now in all peoples account is no ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. She's a perfect Flatterer, and a ſecret Enemy: ſhe'l ſaun upon you like a Spannel, and yet indeavour to cut your Throat. Oh! how ſhe hugs her ſelf when ſhe hath gotten ſomething that ſhe thinks is a ſlanderous report by the end. She makes it her next buſineſſe to augment it &amp; blaze it abroad: Or rather than fail, ſhe'l preſently raiſe a ſcandal upon any body; and when ſhe hath done, kneel down and imprecate bitter things upon her ſelf, and utterly forſwear her words. O, the horred imprecations enough to make ſober people fear the houſe would come down upon their heads, or that the earth as weary of ſuch a ſinfull burden, would open her mouth and ſwallow them up. But if all this will not ſerve, but that ſhe muſt needs confeſs ſomthing, ſhe'l <hi>turn Cat in the Par,</hi> and quite alter the ſtory: or if there be ſuch witneſs, that its impoſſible for her to evade any part of it, then ſhe cryes that ſhe ſpake it in her Ale, or in her Anger: but ſhe ſhall be made to ſuffer for it, when ſhe's Sober or not Angry. And when the laviſhneſs of her tongue hath brought her into ſome danger, ſhe can eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Crocodiles Teares, (with which ſhe would ſeem to waſh away the foulneſſe of her offence) when ſhe hath moſt minde to devour you.</p>
            <p>The cheifeſt accuſations with which ſhe charges every one, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their honeſty: And the reaſon why ſhe ſo much miſdoubts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is becauſe She had never much her ſelfe. Her cheifeſt ſpite is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all young women that live honeſtly; for ſhe would fain have them like her ſelf, that ſo they might not have ſo much cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of her.</p>
            <p>All men that are ſeen at any other houſe then hers, (though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſober or honeſt,) ſhall be preſently tearmed either Drunkards or Whore-maſters; but in her houſe they may be both if they will, without offending her. And all young women in her opinion are Whores, and ſhe will not ſtick to ſay ſo; but <hi>The verieſt Whore cries Whore firſt.</hi> She's an ugly ſnotty Whore her ſelf, and hath given many a ſnotty noſe to others; but more eſpecially to Mr. <hi>E.</hi> who before he could make it clean, blowed out his life: And Mr. <hi>Price</hi> the Chirugion was fain alſo to doſe her with a Medicine to cool her <hi>Aquavitae.</hi> The Daughter alſo begins to follow the Mothers ſteps pretty exactly: for She's of the <hi>Lemman</hi> breed, and <hi>right Lemman</hi> colour, which (what ever others think,) ſhe takes to be no ſtain in her reputation. A few arguments will prevail; ſhe'l prove a windfall with the leaſt breath. I could name ſeveral that have done what they would with her upon the bed by the fire ſide. She begins already to weare the badges of her trade: its none of her goodneſſe that buds out ſo faſt, that ſhe's fain to wear four or five black Patches upon her face at once to cover the Scabs: the heat begins to fly up into her Noſe, which perhaps may bid her adieu ere
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63727:3"/>long. I am ſure her extraction cannot any way intitle her to the Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a gentle-woman; for ſhe was at firſt ſucked out of the Tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole, to which ſhe naturally returns like <hi>a Bitch to her vomit,</hi> and like a Sow to her wallowing in the mire. But why ſhould I be ſo Satyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call? I hope for the future ſhe'l take heed of beſpewing her ſilk Gown again: Her Mother gave hea ſound rattle for it, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her Whore, and told her ſhe could ſit all day at the Pot and the Pipe, and yet not commit ſuch a groſs abſurdity ſo viſibly. In a word, this young Landaprides would fain make her ſelf that which God nor Nature never intended; for if melted greaſe upon turd-colour be handſome, then ſhe may be called Handſome: But if I were deſired to give a Character of her, it ſhould be in ſhort, much to this purpoſe; She's a thing that ſometimes appeares in a ſilke Gown, with black pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on her face, (marry come up here,) and would fain ſeem to be a Gentle-woman, but is indeed nothing but a Tap-wench thats newly ſprung up out of the froth of a black pot; and having paſſed once through her Mothers Alembick, is Chymically converted into the more ſalacious froth, <hi>Venus;</hi> ſo that I need not tell you what ſhe is in plain Engliſh, for her very extraction entitles her to levity, and the foulneſs of the Subject I am now in handling induces me to brevity, (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending another time to give her a whole broad-ſide unleſſe ſhe mends her manners,) that I may return to the buſineſs from whence I have made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome digreſſion.</p>
            <p>Do but aſk the old Devill if ſhe ever knew Colonell <hi>Zouch,</hi> (I could name ſeverall others which I willingly omit,) and mark if her fiery face be not tinctured with a double dye: if ſhe ſayes ſhe never knew him, I ſay he hath <hi>known</hi> her too often, if his own confeſſion be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimony. She was ſerved but a <hi>Sly</hi> trick when one of her companions falling out with her, told her; Oh, ſhe had it in her head, ſhe had it in her head, ſhe'd go make her husband a Cuckold too, that ſhe might have ſome body to take her part. She ſent the poor man out of this miſerable world with ſo great a pair of horns on his head, that probably he could hardly get to heaven; for the way thither is ſaid to be but narrow, and therefore no horned beaſts to come there. Neither did it make much for her credit when her husband went half way to <hi>Bill,</hi> and making a ſhorter return then ſhe expected, came home and found another man in bed with her. She Capricorn'd his Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, and congratulated his return with a <hi>Chaſing-diſh</hi> of Hornicom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtulated Metaphor's. But he told her, if ſhe uſed to play him ſuch leſſons on the <hi>Horn-Pipe,</hi> he would play to her on the <hi>Baggage-Pipe,</hi> and make her dance out of dores. Some Whores uſe to draw mens Lips into their mouths, as if they ſhould ſay <hi>I would have you within me:</hi> But ſhe uſes alſo to thruſt her Tongue into mens mouths, as intimating that ſhe would have them do her a courteſy by thruſting ſomething into her mouth beneath. If ſhe denies any of theſe things I'le ſwear that She's a more impudent lyar then the Devill, and that her Face is nothing but the Bo's of a great Braſs. Andiron beſpangled
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63727:4"/>with Glow-wormes, and ſet upon the rotten Standard of a putryfied body qualified with thoſe conſpicuous Vertues of naturall Diſhoneſty and artificiall Diſſimulation, ſuch as becomes none but her Country-folks the inhabitants of Hell &amp; ſuch as was never known to proceed from any leſs Devills then Lucifer and Belzebub to whom ſhe is great Grandame. But her kiſſing is done at her upper lip, becauſe there's nothing to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the deformity: and almoſt at her lower lip too; and they that have had moſt at either, do now loath her as much as ever they did the ſtinking carkaſſe of an old Whore roaſted with the fire within her own bowells.</p>
            <p>But alas poor woman, ſhe ſhould now be an object of my pitty, not upon whom I ſhould wreak my fury; wherefore I would willingly ſpeake a good word for her to help recover that credit which is loſt: but if I ſhould call her a <hi>proper</hi> woman, it would be falſe Grammar; for ſhe was never known to be <hi>Proper,</hi> but alwayes <hi>Common.</hi> One might imagine her to be <hi>right</hi> in all her dealings; in ſome ſhe's ſure enough <hi>as right as one's legg,</hi> for ſhe hath alwayes been ready to <hi>do</hi> with other men as ſhe would have them <hi>do</hi> with her. She ſhould ſeem to be valiant, for ſhe'l bring down three or four luſty men upon their knees, and more too if the firſt ſhould not <hi>ſtop her courſe.</hi> The way how ſhe ſo eaſily overcomes, is thus; ſhe fights like a Bear lying on her back, and if any man comes at her with a ſingle Rapier, ſhe draws him <hi>in</hi> preſently. Thus ſhe thinkes to fright men by giving them the forked end: And to ſpeake truly, I believe ſhe hath ſomething there that's enough to frighten any man that would poſſibly be frighted. I pray you object not that ſhe's poor and beggarly, for ſhe hath made ſhift to get her Daughter a ſilk Gown, though ſhe be but <hi>old Mother Red-Coat,</hi> herſelf: and you onght not to blame her, ſeeing ſhe cannot now ſo much as ſhe uſed to do, lye backward her ſelf, and let out her fore-roomes; eſpecially not at ſo high a rate as when <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> was beſeiged: that was then a great part of her livelihood. But yet ſhe hath a colts tooth, ſhe'l lap as much as two young kitlings if any man would give it her: ſhe'l milk the Bull as well ever an old Cow in this Shire: She's never ſatiated, as you know the fire will devour all <hi>things,</hi> and <hi>burn</hi> them too, if they come there. I might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her for a great linguiſt, for ſhe hath a double tongue, and and as much language as would ſerve half a dozen women: and ſhe ſpeakes <hi>The French</hi> as perfectly as any woman in Turnbull ſtreet. She would ſurely make a good Trumpeter, for ſhe hath a ſtrong breath: Neighbours, pray you keep your dores and windows cloſe ſhut, for when ſhe opens her lips, there comes forth a ſtench more noiſome then that of a Charnell houſe, the ſent of her rotten trunk is more infectious then the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. You may know where ſhe is before you ſee her, for you may ſmell her long before you come at her; but I think he that hath ſeen her once, will never deſire to ſee her again. Thus when I go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to commend her, I am apt by ſiſting a freſh, to find ſome other faults: Yet I might ſay ſhe's pleaſant and lightſome; but you'l ſay
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63727:4"/>ſhe's light all: and I know ſhe's light enough in a double ſenſe, but it ſerves only like an <hi>Ignis fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> to miſlead men running between the legs. Nay, if you knew all, you might think her a Witch, becauſe ſhe's <hi>burnt</hi> alive: but rather ſhe ſhould ſeem a Phanatick, becauſe ſhe's al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes led by the light within her; and therefore can ſeldome erre, for for if ſhe doth but follow her Noſe, ſhe follows Torch-light: or, for failing, her Belly may ſerve for a dark Lanthorn, for ſhe alwayes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries a pocky fire in it. She may be thought a Phariſee, for ſhe affects (more then becomes tap-wives) the higheſt ſeat in the Church: Nay, ſhe is ſo delighted in climing, that when ſhe's at home, ſhe'l clime up ſometimes ten <hi>Steries</hi> high, and like a Jugler, alwayes preſent you with falſe things inſtead of true. But what ever our miſapprehenſions may be, ſhe'l be found at laſt to be a Fiſher: Yet I am ſure ſhe's no Kings Fiſher; for when ſhe appeares, 'tis more the ſign of a Tempeſt then a Calm. But ſhe's a Fiſher of Men, ſhe catches fleſh far ofteneſt: and if they have but half a Crown to pay ſees, all is fiſh that comes to her Net. But what do I talk of? She's a Planet, both a <hi>Deceiver</hi> and a <hi>Wanderer,</hi> the Character of a Whore; for her feet abide not in her own houſe. If you aſk what Planet, I anſwer ſhe's very Martiall, fierce and full of contention: yea, ſhe ſhould be altogether <hi>Mars</hi> by that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bified beſpangled conſtellation of her countenance: yet from ſome of her qualities I might tearm her <hi>Verus,</hi> but that ſhe's none of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, nor none of the faireſt, and is alwayes combuſt <hi>under</hi> the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bcames.</p>
            <p>But for all this that hath been ſaid, I think ſhe hath a better opinion of her ſelfe then others have of her; otherwiſe ſhe would never <hi>ly?</hi> ſo ecure at open guard, and lay her ſelfe open to the world that all men may <hi>do</hi> what they will, but that ſhe deems her vertuous actions (though they be but few,) may redeem her credit (which is but ſmall) which yet ſhe imagines not ſo much diminiſhed, becauſe (whatſoever he actions he) ſhe thinks ſhe may do what ſhe will becauſe ſhe hath alwaves a good colour for it.</p>
            <p>But now I'le make haſt, becauſe I begin to perceive in her ſome Symptomes of mortality: her good name is already buried before her; I ſuppoſe her carkaſs will follow ere long, for ſhe ſtinks above ground. Yet rather then want a Name, ſhe ſhall have a bad one, &amp; ſhe ſhall be rebaptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it is <hi>Styx</hi> the black river of Hell, that ſo the pitch that ſhall ſtick up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her fore-head, may be a worſe brand of her infamy then that of <hi>Cain's.</hi> She ſhall be named <hi>Alecto-Tyſiphone-Megaera,</hi> for all the three Furies join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together make up but one Mrs. Fiſher. A wiſp, a wiſp, and a cucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool for the Butter-whore: all the Huckſters at Carſax and Oyſter-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at Billings-gate cannot be heard ſo far as ſhe by a quarter of a mile. She is not compoſed of the Four Elements like other creatures, ſhe owes her originall onely to fire and water; and they two meeting in one, may be the reaſon why the Thunder and Lightning come ſo oft from her Coaſts. The predominancy of the Sulphur is a ſufficient indication of the inequality of her compoſure, by which ſhe cannot
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63727:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>live long: nay, ſhe had never ſurvived hitherto, but that <hi>Atropos</hi> with a dull knif vowed to give her many a ſore ſcotch ere ſhe ſhould be put out of her pain. But the ſtench of her corps doth ſo anoy me, that I am now forced to forſake her, and leave her to the next ditch or dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, having already according to her own deſerts laid her open to the world.</p>
            <p>There's a great deal more behind, which I omit at Preſent, being unwilling to defile any more clean paper with ſo foul a ſubject. I am only ſorry that I have ſo taken my fare-well of the Univerſity, that I cannot be there preſent to give Verball teſtimony to what I have here written. But all that know her, know all I have ſaid to be true, and a great deal more, which you ſhall have next opportunity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
